<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exhortation to his dearely beloued countrimen, all the natiues of the countie of Lancaster, inhabiting in and about the Citie of London; tending to perswade and stirre them vp to a yearely contribution, for the erecting of lectures, and maintaining of some godly and painfull preachers in such places of that country as have most neede, by reason of ignorance and superstition there abounding: / composed by George Walker pastor of St. Iohn the Euangelists ...</title>
            <author>Walker, George, B.D., d. 1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10261</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80925282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W357A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186166</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80925282</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80925282</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192164</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192164)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2901:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exhortation to his dearely beloued countrimen, all the natiues of the countie of Lancaster, inhabiting in and about the Citie of London; tending to perswade and stirre them vp to a yearely contribution, for the erecting of lectures, and maintaining of some godly and painfull preachers in such places of that country as have most neede, by reason of ignorance and superstition there abounding: / composed by George Walker pastor of St. Iohn the Euangelists ...</title>
                  <author>Walker, George, B.D., d. 1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and social problems --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Early works to 1800..</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:192164:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192164:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An exhortation to his Dearely beloued Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen, all the Natiues of the Countie of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſter,</hi> inhabiting in and about the Citie of <hi>London;</hi> tending to perſwade and ſtirre them vp to a yearely contribution, for the erecting of Lectures, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of ſome godly and painfull preachers in ſuch places of that Country as haue moſt neede, by reaſon of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and ſuperſtition there abounding: compoſed by <hi>George Walker</hi> Paſtor of St. <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Euangeliſts</hi> in <hi>Watlingſtreet</hi> in <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MY deare and louing Countrimen, whom God by his gracious prouidence hath together with my ſelfe, tranſplanted out of our natiue Country the Countie of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> (which, as it is at this day, ſo hath much more in the dayes of our youth and within our memorie, beene as a rough, vntilled barren deſert, ouer-runne with ignorance, ſuperſtition and poperie) and hath planted vs by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of comfort in a wealthy and fruitfull place, where all bleſſings needfull for ſoule and body are extended vnto vs as a flowing ſtreame:
<note place="margin">Iſai 66.12. Luke 12.48.</note> you are not ignorant of that ſaying of our Sauiour, That <hi>to whom much is giuen, of them much ſhall be required:</hi> yea I doubt not but ye haue all learned this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; that as God after grear deliuerance from great euills, dangers and miſeries requires much thankfulneſſe to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at the hands of the deliuered: ſo alſo much compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards their brethren, who ſtill remaine in the ſame mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and dangers, and a readineſſe to helpe and ſuccour them vpon euery occaſion and opportunity which ſhall bee offered. This our Sauiour teacheth vs by his example and continuall practiſe, in that he is <hi>touched with our infirmities, and by the things which hee ſuffered being tempted,
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.15. and 2, 18.</note> is become a mercifull high Preiſt able and readie to ſuccour them that are tempted:</hi> And this hee enjoynes vs all to put in practiſe, in that charge which he gaue to his Apoſtle? <hi>when thou are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192164:2"/>conuerted ſtrengthen thy brethren.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 22.32. Iohn 13.17.</note> Now my brethren <hi>if ye know theſe things, happy</hi> and bleſſed ſhall you be <hi>if ye</hi> alſo <hi>doe them,</hi> as our Sauiour affirmeth in the Goſpell. And that you may by ſo doing obteine more eaſily this happineſſe and bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: lo here I will ſhew you a ſhort cut and a ready way, euen one only worke of piety and charity which I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto you, in which worke alone (if you ſhall wiſely and conſcionably begin it, and therein carefully, cheerfully and conſtantly proceed and continue to the end according to that ability which God hath giuen to you) ye ſhall at once performe all theſe workes and duties of Chriſtianitie; that is, you ſhall render and returne vnto God increaſe and fruit according to the talents which he hath committed to your truſt, and the ſeed and coſt of planting and tilling which he hath on you beſtowed; you ſhall offer vp to his majeſtie a moſt acceptable ſacrifice of thankfulneſſe for his deliuerance of your ſoules from dangers of ignorance, ſuperſtition and prophaneſſe which ouer-ſpread the place of your natiuitie, and withall you ſhall ſhew all Chriſtian compaſſion, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e brotherly charity and commiſeration rowards your brethren and Country, and by Gods grace and bleſſing on your indeauours, become powerfull inſtruments and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall meanes of ſauing many ſoules;
<note place="margin">Acts 28.18.</note> by turning them from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan vnto God: that they may become fellow Saints with your ſelues,
<note place="margin">Colloſſ. 1.12.</note> and coheires and partakers of the inheritance of glory in light.</p>
            <p>This worke (to deſcribe and ſet it forth plainely in that nature as it is here commended to you) is no more but a free, voluntary, cheerfull and charitable contribution of ſuch yearly ſummes of money, as euery one of you, by means of that wealth and ability which God hath beſtowed vpon him, may very well without impoueriſhing, pinching, or any way ouercharging of himſelfe, or impairing of his eſtate, beſtow for the maintaining of godly, painefull and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble preachers of Gods word in thoſe parrs and pariſhes of our natiue Country of <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> in which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere is found to be greateſt need, and moſt grieuous want &amp; ſcarſity of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192164:2"/>and maintenance for preachers; that by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall labors, zealous preaching and conſcionable paines, ignorance and ſuperſtition may be rooted out, true religion planted, Gods true worſhip ſet vp and eſtabliſhed, and that by the conuerting of many ſoules, and inſtructing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirming the weake, Gods true Church may there increaſe and flouriſh, and ſo that Country which is now in many places like a barren wilderneſſe, may become a fruitfull gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and pleaſant vineyard of the Lord of hoſts, well watered with plentifull ſhowers of Gods heauenly and ſpirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces diſtilling from heauen, and with fountaines, ſprings and flowing ſtreames of earthly and temporall bleſſings, which follow and accompanie the publike enterteinment of the Goſpell, and the aduancement of Chriſts true Church in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery land.</p>
            <p>This worke (if wee ſhould ſeeke no further but looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and take a view of it in it ſelfe, as it is here in plaine words propounded to vs) hath in it motiues ſufficient of all ſorts to draw vs, and moue vs to put it in preſent practiſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whereas in many other workes of bountie and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, grace and nature are ſound contrary, and while the one perſwades vs to doe them, the other diſſwades vs from them; as for example, in the purchaſing of great houſes, lands and reuenues for our children, while naturall affection doth incite vs to disburſe great ſummes, and to imploy all out wealth and eſtate; Grace on the contrary forbids vs to ſpend all on our children and fleſhly kinred, which perhaps may proue wicked prodigalls, and abuſe our riches to ſinne and miſchiefe, and tells vs that we ought rather to honour God with our wealth, by ſpending a great part there of in workes of piety and charity vpon the poore members of Chriſt: And while Grace drawes vs to this, naturall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth draw and pull vs from it, vnto the other. Now in this worke here commended to you there is no ſuch oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition betweene grace and nature, nor any ſuch cauſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, but both together doe draw, pull and allure vs with ioynt forces: Grace tells vs that this being a worke of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192164:3"/>pitty tending to Gods glory by the ſauing of many ſoules, the increaſe of his Church, and aduancement of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and his holy worſhippe, no good Chriſtian can refuſe to put his hand vnto it; but euery one ought to be, and will be forward in it. And becauſe this worke is alſo a worke of charitie not towards ſtrangers; but towards our Countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and kinred according to the fleſh, euen towards our owne brethren, and tends to this as one maine end to make our natiue Country bleſſed with all bleſſings heauenly and earthly; therefore naturall affection doth ſtrongly and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently pull vs and perſwade vs vnto it, and as we all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally loue our Country and kinred; ſo we cannot but by the inſtinct of nature be forward in this worke.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this contribution is not like thoſe antique taxes, which heathen Emperours, tyrants rather, vſed by their conſtraining commandements, and with ſtrong hand to wreſt from their euer-awed &amp; impotent vaſſals; nor like the rigid pennance and grieuous penalties, which Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſts and confeſſors doe often times inflict on their penitents as a ſatisfaction for their ſinnes; which either are aboue the ſtrength of their bodies, and tend to the endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering of their health and life, or ſurpaſſe their abilities and eſtates, and doe farre ouer-charge and much impoueriſh them; but this is onely of ſo much as the ſpirit of God ſhall inwardly moue and perſwade euery man to giue freely and cheerfully with all alacritie, and which God hath inabled him to giue without impoueriſhing of himſelfe, or weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and impairing of his eſtate, and which may well be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from other vaine expenſes and needleſſe ſuperfluities: ſo that here is no coulout of exception againſt this contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution, no leaſt cauſe for any to complaine, grudge or murmure againſt it, or to count it a burden: here is nothing required of any but what he is able and willing to doe, and that without any wrong, loſſe or damage to himſelfe at all.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this worke is not one of thoſe almes-deeds and workes of charity which are done in ſecret, which few ſee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:192164:3"/>but God; this is a publike worke like a candle vpon a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſticke which giues light to all the houſe, beſides the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and comfort which it may bring to many and ſeuerall particular ſoules, and the gracious acceptation and bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reward which it may find with God; it ſhall vndoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly alſo bring great glory to Gods name, and be a meanes of many thankes giuen by many vnto God in his publicke Church and congregation. And as the multitude of them who receiue the benefit of this contribution, ſhall haue iuſt cauſe to laud and praiſe God continually: ſo many others, euen all they who ſee it a farre of and heare the fame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of it, ſhall be prouoked and ſtirred vp by your example; and hereby you ſhall cauſe your lights to ſhine before men, <hi>that they ſeeing your good workes, may glorifie your father which is in heauen,</hi> as our Sauiour in the Goſpell exhorteth. And whereas in other caſes a worke of piety tending to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good cannot be done without great coſt and charge, and requires a great ſumme: here in this contribution eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular man may for a ſmall oblation offered vp with a free heart obtaine the honour, and gaine the glory of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke worke, and become an example and patterne of piety to many others, and ſo bring great glory to God, and much benefit to the Church of Chriſt, with ſmall charge to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by reaſon of many hearts and hands conſpiring toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this one worke.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, in many other workes of piety and charitie, there are many doubts and diſcouragements often times; as for example, when a man muſt lay out a great ſumme, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon a great hazard and aduenture, being vncertaine whether it ſhall take good effect, and yeeld any fruit at all to himſelfe or thoſe to whom he doth intend it; as we ſee in many hoſpitalls and Colleges much ſubject to abuſe; the coſt beſtowed vpon which is like <hi>bread caſt vpon the waters,</hi> onely in hope of <hi>finding it after many dayes</hi> as wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.1. Or when much is giuen away by men at their death in their laſt will to pious vſes, of which they themſelues being dead, can reape no benefit at all from the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192164:4"/>prayers of the poore who enjoy it, as blind Papiſts would perſwade the world; nor any comfort from the ſight of the good fruit which it yeelds to poſterity. But here in this contribution there is no ſuch cauſe of doubting, nor any ſuch ſcruple to diſhearten any man: here is no great ſumme to bee aduentured or put forth vpon vncertainties; but a ſmall yearly bencuolence to be paid quarterly, &amp; continued ſo long only as it ſhall manifeſtly appear, to be well imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to good purpoſe &amp; for preſent profit, which payment alſo euery man ſhall haue in his power for his owne part to ceaſe breake off and diſcontinue, if he doth ſee no manifeſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thence preſently ariſing according to his deſire; but if it doth take good effect, it ſhall much aduance Gods glory before men, bring comfort, light and ſauing health to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſoules, and procure to the contributors many hearty prayers of their Country-men, who ſhall by this meanes be conuerted and comforted; which prayers vndoubtedly God will heare and accept, and at their requeſt turne many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings into their boſomes here in this life, where onely the prayers and thankſgiuing of Gods people, haue power to helpe and profit thoſe for whom they are made and offered vp in the name and mediation of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, whoſoeuer hath a deſire to put forth his talent of worldly wealth whatſoeuer it is more or leſſe to the beſt aduantage, and ſo to imploy it that it may bring in double and trible gaine, ſurely he cannot finde a better way then this pious worke which is here commended vnto you. For the firſt and immediate end of this contribution is the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp and maintaining of godly, painfull and profitable preachers of Gods word in thoſe parts of our natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where the word of God is moſt rare and precious, and there is greateſt neede and ſcarſitie of preaching. Wee doe not meane to feede idle droanes, who will labour but little, and looke for large allowance; nor ſuch as will labour and take paines but to ſmall profit, for want of the art of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying, and method of profitable preaching; nor men of ſcandalous and vngodly life, who will doe more hurt by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192164:4"/>their example, then good by their doctrine: But godly, painefull and profitable preachers, who will preach and teach, and labour out of conſcience to God, with an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring and thirſting deſire, not to get wealth and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but to ſaue many ſoules, and to increaſe the Church of Chriſt, who alſo for a ſmall ſtipend will take much pains, and will teach as well by good example, as by doctrine. Now where ſuch preachers are ſet vp and maintained, there will follow plentifull preaching and hearing of the word of God, the word heard will beget faith, and bring many to beleeue in God and in Chriſt; faith will bring forth the the true worſhip of God, and holy inuocation or calling vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his name; and true, deuout and faithfull calling vpon the name of the Lord, is the ſure way to ſaluation, as may eaſily be gathered from the words of the holy Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.13, 14, 15. But eſpecially when ſuch preachers are ſent into barren places, and among a people ouer-runne with ignorance, ſuperſtition and profaneſſe for want of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as in our natiue Country; they doe more preuaile with their godly labours, and bring more plentifull fruit, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to Gods Church in one yeare, and work more ſtrang effects by turning many ſoules from darkneſſe to light, from profaneſſe to piety, from ignorance and ſuperſtition, to the ſauing knowledge and true worſhip of God, and from the ſlauery and power of Satan, vnto the glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Gods children, as experience in ſome parts of our Country hath of late proued; then many others as worthy and well quallified as they, or they themſelues are able to doe in theſe parts where the light of the Goſpell hath ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the dayes of our fore-fathers. For as it is with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilled ground, ouer-growne with briets, weeds and thornes; the firſt yeares plowing, ſowing and manuring of it, doth worke a greater and more viſible change from barrenneſſe to fruitfulneſſe, then all plowing and manuring can doe in ground well tilled before, becauſe that onely continueth and increaſeth the old, doth not beget new fruitfulneſſe: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it is with a people when the word is ſent firſt among
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192164:5"/>them; If it doth preuaile with them at all, and if they doe not vtterly reject, but chearfully receiue it, they are more viſibly changed from profaneſſe and ſuperſtition, to piety and profeſſion of true religion in the firſt yeare, then in a long time and many yeares after, ſo that both the preachers which labor among them, and the godly contributors who ſet them vp and maintaine them, may behold with joy and gladneſſe of heart aboundance of preſent fruit and increaſe ariſing from ſmall coſt and labour, which is a ſtrong motiue and encouragement to all Chriſtians thus to imploy their talents which God hath committed to them, and to ſhew and exerciſe their charity and piety in this kind. To all theſe ſpirituall motiues and in couragements ariſing from ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in creaſe, profit and benefit, we may adde the multitude and aboundance of temporall bleſſings and benefits which the Goſpell brings with it to the Country and people, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom it is generally and with publike conſent recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and imbraced; For experience hath taught the world in all ages, that as the heate and light of the Sunne accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with watering ſhowers of raine and dew, doe make the earth fruitfull in corne, wine, oyle, and all other fruites which are required either for the profit and benefit, or for the pleaſure and delight of man: So the light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell working the heate of true zeale in the hearts of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and drawing from them the teares of true repentance, and cauſing many ſuch ſhowers of heauenly moyſture to diſtill from their eyes; neuer hath failed, but in all ages hath brought all ſtore euen of earthly bleſſings with it, and made Gods Saints and people honourable, renowned, and of high eſteeme, for their worldly greatneſſe, wealth and proſperity in the eyes of the heathen nations among whom they haue liued. This was that which made religious and vpright <hi>Noah</hi> not onely the heire of the righteouſneſſe which is by faith, but alſo brought temporall deliuerance, and bodily ſafety to him and his family, in the vniuerfall deluge and deſtruction of the old world, and made him and his ſonnes the repairers of mankind, and the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192164:5"/>of the new world which followed, as the Apoſtle hath obſerued <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7. This made <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> the Prieſt &amp; ſacrificer of the high God, to liue and reigne a King of peace in all plenty and proſperity in the midſt of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Canaanites,</hi> while all the bordering Kings and neighbors were ouer-runne with the calamities of warre, and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the heauy yoke and bondage vnder <hi>Chedarlaomer,</hi> and other forraigne tyrants as we may reade <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. This made <hi>Abraham,</hi> the father of the faithfull, and <hi>Iſaae</hi> his ſon the heire of promiſe, ſo to proſper and flouriſh in all proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, wealth and riches, that the heathen nations among whom they ſojourned as ſtrangers, did eſteeme and ſtile them Princes of God; and potent Kings ſought vnto them to enter into a league and oath of amity with them, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.2, 6. &amp; 21.22. &amp; 23 6. &amp; 26.28. This made <hi>Iacob</hi> who fled ouer <hi>Iordan</hi> to his vncle <hi>Laban</hi> with a ſtaffe in his hand, ſo to grow, increaſe and proſper, that he returned with oxen, aſſes, flocks, man-ſeruants and women-ſeruants, wiues and children, which made vp two troupes or bands as he himſelfe confeſſeth to the glory of God that gaue them: <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.5.10. This made <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to proſper euen in all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affaires, and all things whereunto he put his hand, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.2.3.23. This brought all bleſſings of victory ouer ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies abroad, and of peace and plenty at home, with all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, fame and renowne, to <hi>Dauid, Hezechiah, Ioſiah</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther religious Kings of <hi>Iſraell</hi> and <hi>Iudah;</hi> who receiued and beleeued the word of God, &amp; obeyed it with all their hearts. And that large promiſe which God made to <hi>Ioſhua</hi> the firſt Iudge and ruler ouer <hi>Iſraell</hi> after <hi>Moſes,</hi> viz. that of he would religiouſly obey his word and law, not turning from it to the right hand or the left; he ſhould certainly proſper whitherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he did go; &amp; in all things haue good ſucceſſe: <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1.7, 8 that ſame he actually performed, verified and made good not onely to him, and to all the people of <hi>Iſraell</hi> in his dayes: but alſo to all the godly and religious Iudges which ſucceeded him, and to the whole nation of the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their gouernment, as appeares <hi>Iudg.</hi> 2.18. And leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:192164:6"/>ſhould thinke that theſe examples recorded in Scripture were extraordinary and miraculous; we haue alſo experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the like in all ages, and euen in this age, and in this land wherein we liue. For notwithſtanding all the Popes curſes and thunder-bolts, and all the open aſſaults which he hath made, and the ſecret conſpiracy which he hath put in practiſe againſt this land, incenſing and ſtirring vp all his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of violence and cruelty againſt it, yet both in the dayes of King <hi>Edward</hi> and of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of bleſſed memorie, who reformed religion, and maintained the true preaching of the Goſpell by publike authority; this Land and Church hath proſpered and flouriſhed, and in all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peace, plenty and proſperity excelled all other nations and Churches of the world. So that we may all vpon good experience with one mouth confeſſe, that true religion and the holy Goſpell of Chriſt, which we haue receiued and lodged in this land vnder the reigne of our later Kings haue proued moſt profitable gueſts vnto vs; they haue ouer and aboue the aboundance of heauenly knowledge, and ſauing graces which belong to eternall ſaluation, out of their more then Kingly bounty royally paid vs with all ſafety, ſecurity, peace, proſperity and plenty of all worldly bleſſings: yea we haue plaine promiſes and teſtimonies in the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that thus it ſhall be to all people of all nations, who receiue and embrace the Goſpell in ſyncerity and truth, and profeſſe true religion without hypocriſie. Our Sauiour in the Goſpell promiſeth, that if any <hi>ſeeke first the kingdome of God and the righteouſneſſe thereof, they ſhall haue all other world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſings, (which the Gentiles ſo carefully ſeeke) ouer and aboue added vnto them: Matth.</hi> 6.33. And in another place hee promiſeth to ſuch as renounce and forſake the things of this world for his ſake and for loue to the Goſpell, that they ſhall <hi>receiue (be ſides life euerlaſting in the world to come) an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th-fold more</hi> euen of theſe earthly bleſſings h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re in this life: <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.30. To which purpoſe we haue a moſt cleare reſtimonie of the holy Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paut</hi> a <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. where he ſaith, that <hi>godlineſſe is profitable vnto all things hauing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:192164:6"/>of the life that now is, as well as of that which is to come.</hi> Vpon theſe ſure and infallible grounds both of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and common experience, I dare be bold to aſſure you (my deare Countri-men) that if you heartily and vnſeined<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire to ſee your natiue Country and kindred flouriſh in all worldly wealth and earthly proſperitie, you cannot for the obteining of your deſire in all the world find a more ready way, then this worke of piety which I here commend vnto you, which as it tends firſt to plant the Goſpell and true religion, ſo it will draw on all other bleſſings by meanes of them.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe motiues which ariſe from the conſideration of the worke it ſelfe, our natiue Countrie alſo, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and diſpoſition of the people for whoſe vſe and benefit this worke is intended, doe moreouer afford and offer vnto vs many ſtrong incouragements. For wee are not to deale with a ſtubborne, bruitiſh ill natured people like the wild Iriſh, who naturally abhorre all ciuility, and are ſo deuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to their owne old faſhions, that things which in themſelues are moſt reaſonable, decent and orderly, they doe vtterly deteſt if they appeare to ſwerue from the corrupt and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable cuſtomes of their Country, and the traditions of their fathers: The people of our natiue Country are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of another conſtitution, and of a contrarie but farre better naturall diſpoſition; although they are moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in their reſolutions, while they conceiue and imagine them to be iuſt, good and godly, and doe follow that courſe of religion and life, which they haue embraced for the beſt with ſtrong affection and zeale; yet naturally they are ſo ingenious, and ſo reaſonable and tractable, that when good reaſon is ſhewed to them for the contrary, they are ready as to conceiue and vnderſtand it, ſo to yeeld vnto it generally and for the moſt part: (onely ſome deſperate reprobates, and refractarie rebells excepted, whom God for their wilfull reiecting of the truth, hath giuen ouer to bee blinded and bewitched by the deluſion and inchantments of Popiſh Prieſts and Ieſuites, and to be poſſeſſed by their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:192164:7"/>diabolicall ſpirit.) And (if we may giue credit to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hiſtoriographers who haue narrowly ſearched, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a diligent ſurvey of all the ſhires of this Kingdome, and obſerued and noted in their publike records and writings the manners of the people) as the inhabitants of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> are in bodily feature and outward forme generally more beautifull and comely, then in many other Countries; ſo in reſpect of the inward diſpoſition of their mindes they are euery way anſwerable, that it is a people of good vnderſtanding, quicke of apprehenſion, well tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in their wills and affections, and ready to be ruled by reaſon: So that if any ſhall object againſt this our good motion, and oppoſe as a barre or obſtacle againſt it the blind zeale and head-ſtrong affection, wherewith a great part of our natiue Country, and many of our people in diuers parts thereof are carried away from the truth and true religion, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Popiſh ſuperſtition and Idolatrie; and ſhall from thence conclude, that in all likeli-hood and probabilitie, our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution of money, and the labours of our preachers ſhalbe ſpent in vaine, and for no profit, on a refractarie and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate people, who like <hi>deafe adders will ſtop their eares, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to heare the voyce of the charmers, charme they neuer ſo wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as they haue done heretofore euer ſince the firſt reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Goſpell and reformation of religion in this Kingdome: I will anſwere, that this which is objected as a barre or impediment, is indeed none all to ſuch as rightly vnderſtand and conſider it; but on the contrary offers to our conſideration ſpeciall incouragements and motiues to further vs in this worke. For firſt, true Chriſtianity teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs to ſhew mercy and charity to our brethren in miſerie and bondage, and the greater we perceiue that their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and miſerie is wherein they remaine, the more to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moued inwardly with pitty and compaſſion towards them, and rather then we will in dure the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight of their continuall extremities, to make a deſperate attempt for their deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and to aduenture vpon a great hazard euen when there is little or no hope of their recouerie in outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:192164:7"/>We haue many examples of Gods faithfull Saints recorded in the Scripture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to this purpoſe: The penitent <hi>Iſraelites</hi> captiued in <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſo often and ſo long as they remembred <hi>Zious deſolation,</hi> and the deplored eſtate of their natiue Country, could joy in nothing, but ſpent their time in weeping and in ſtudying the good and proſperity of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem: Pſal.</hi> 137. Queene <hi>Hester</hi> when her people the <hi>Iewes</hi> were in extreme danger, by reaſon of a Commiſſion or warrant ſealed for the generall maſſacre and deſtruction of them all, did run in a deſperate hazard euen of her owne life, and reſolued for their deliuerance to attempt the recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Kings vnchangeable decree, ſaying, <hi>If I periſh, I periſh: Heſt:</hi> 4.16. And godly <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> when he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued intelligence of the great affliction and reproach of his brethren in <hi>Indea</hi> after their returne from captiuity, and of the City and place of his fathers ſepulchre lying waſt and conſumed with fire, was ſo ſad and heauy, that he could not reſt nor looke cheerfully on the King his Lord, vntill by earneſt prayer to God and petition to the King, he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed and gotten leaue to goe with a large commiſſion for the repairing of <hi>Ieruſalem: Nehem.</hi> 1 and 2. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the more ſtiffe-necked that he found the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and the more zealous with blind zeale not according to knowledge, the more he pittied them being his Country-men, and the more he laboured by all meanes to win them, and ſought to ſaue ſome of them though it were with the loſſe of his owne life, as appeares <hi>Act.</hi> 24.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.1, 2. And he who is the example of all examples, and the patterne whom all Chriſtians are bound to follow, our Lord &amp; Sauiour Chriſt, when wee all were in a deſperate and wofull condition by meanes of our ſinfull corruption and many ſinnes rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly committed againſt God, from which the whole world was not able to redeeme vs, did not caſt vs off, but vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke a worke for vs, and did vndergoe a burden vnder which all the Angells of God, and all creatures would faint, faile and ſinke downe if it were laid vpon them. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as we deſire to walke in the wayes of Gods Sainte, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192164:8"/>to conforme our ſelues to our head Chriſt: ſo let the great danger of our natiue Country and Country-men in which they lye, and the ſlauiſh ſuperſtition and blindnes by which their ſoules as well as their bodies are held in captiuitie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Pope and the Deuill, ſtirre vs vp to vſe this and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes which God hath reuealed in his word, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of all ages hath diſcourered to be helpfull remedies againſt all ſuch maladies.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If we examine the cauſe of this head-ſtrong blind zeale which ouer-ſpreades our Country, and take true notice of the meanes which maintaine this Popiſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and ignorance in our people; they will appeare to bee ſuch as may juſtly more incourage vs in this worke, then any way diſhearten or diſcourage vs from it. It is true that ſome places, Cities and Countries for ſome notorious pollution are hated and curſed of God, and ſet apart to bee ſpectales of his wrathfull vengeance, and examples of dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful I deſolation, as the plaine Countrie and Citries of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha:</hi> And ſome people are reprobates, whom God in his ſecret counſell hath rejected, and therefore either doth with-hold from them all meanes of ſaluation, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them like ſwine, before whom he will not caſt the precious pearles of his word and ſaraments at all, as we haue plaine examples <hi>Act.</hi> 16. where the Spirit ſorbad the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and would not ſuffer them to goe to preach in ſome Countries, and to ſome people: or elſe doth ſend his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and the miniſters of his word and ſacraments vnto them, not for their good to conuert them, but as a curſe for their greater condemnation to harden them, as his word and miracles by <hi>Moſes</hi> were ſent to <hi>Pharaoh, Exod.</hi> 7.3. and to be vnto them as the Goſpell preached is to periſhing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates, euen <hi>the ſauour of death vnto death:</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. Now when and where ignorance, ſuperſtition and blind z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ale proceede from theſe cauſes and grounds, they are deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and incurable, and whatſoeuer coſt or labour is there beſtowed proues vaine, &amp; is like water ſpilt on the ground. But ſometimes ignorance, blind zeale, ſuperſtition and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:192164:8"/>are found to ouer-ſpread ſome Countries, and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to poſſeſſe ſome people through want of means and good inſtruction, becauſe God ſuffers his word and Goſpell to be with-held from them for a time, either through the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and negligence of their rulers and ouerſeers, vpon whom hee hath a purpoſe to execute his juſt wrath to the full, by bringing vpon them the blood of many poore ſoules which through their default doe periſh; or elſe for to trie, proue and exerciſe the charity of their brethren and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, who are called and conuerted already before them, and haue receiued grace to bee Gods people, whom the Lord hath a purpoſe to prouoke to pittie and charitie, by ſetting before them ſuch examples of miſerable blindneſſe, which haue great neede of their helpe and commiſeration: In theſe caſes, the greateſt ignorance, moſt blind ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and moſt head-ſtrong zeale, ſtanding for errors and a falſe religion, are not deſperate, but haue great hope of cure by the word of God, and ſuch meanes applied to them; yea ſuch head-ſtrong, zealous and ſuperſtitious people, when the true and cleare light of the Goſpell once ſhines vnto them by meanes of an able and powerfull miniſtery, are by experience found to become no leſſe, but rather more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the truth, and for God and godlineſſe, then before they haue beene for falſhood and errors. And that this is the very caſe and condition of our natiue Country, and of our blind, zealous and ſuperſtitious brethren and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours inhabiting, it appeares plainly by two ſtrong and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible arguments.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that their ignorance and blind zeale proceede from want of ordinary meanes, to wit, the preaching of the word and good inſtruction, experience plainely proues, and no man can with any colour of reaſon denie: For although our Country of <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> is one of the largeſt ſhires in this Kingdome, yet it hath for the publike worſhip of God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thirty ſix Pariſh Churches within the large circuite of it, as our hiſtories ſhew, and ſome Pariſhes forty miles in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe to my knowledge, wheras ſome other ſhires not much
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192164:9"/>larger then one diniſion or hundred of <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> are knowne and recorded to haue two or three hundred Pariſh Churches in them, and thoſe farre better furniſhed with meanes for maintenance of an able miniſtery then ours are: for example the hundred of Fourneſſe where I was borne, which for ſpatious compaſſe of ground is not much leſſe then <hi>Bedfordſhire</hi> or <hi>Rutlandſhire,</hi> it hath onely eight Pariſh Churches, and ſeuen of thoſe eight are impropriate, and the liuings in the hands of Lay men, and in ſome of thoſe Pariſhes which be forty miles in compaſſe, there is no more ordinary and ſet maintenance allowed for the miniſtery of the word and ſacraments, but ten pounds or twenty nobles yearly. And therefore though the people were naturally the moſt tractable vnder the Sunne, no man could in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon looke for any thing but abundance of ignorance ruling among them, till it pleaſe God to ſtirre vp the publicke ſtate, or the ſpirits of ſome godly priuate Chriſtians, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide ſome maintenance for the conſtant miniſtery of the word, to be ſet vp and continued among them: yea (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what large ſpacious walkes, and how many couerts and lurking places there are in thoſe thicke miſts and ſhades of ignorance and darkneſſe for Ieſuites and ſeminary Prieſts thoſe ſonnes and miniſters of darkneſſe, who commonly find beſt intertainment for their flattery and painted hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie among ſuch people, as being naturally diſpoſed to deuotion and religion, are notwithſtanding held captiue in ignorance for want of meanes: and alſo finde moſt liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and beſt roome to beſtirre thmſelues, and greateſt free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from diſcouerie in thoſe Pariſhes, where there are no learned Preachers, nor vigilant Paſtors:) let reaſon judge how vnlikely and almoſt impoſſible it is for that people to be free from blind head-ſtrong zeale, and that Popiſh ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and Idolatrie ſhould not generally poſſeſſe them?</p>
            <p>Secondly, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> argues for the nation of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Iſraelites Rom.</hi> 11.1. and proues that they were not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly caſt away of God, becauſe hee himſelfe and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of them were gathered vnto Chriſt by the Goſpell,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:192164:9"/>and an elect remnant was found among them in the dayes of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, when generally they perſecuted the truth, and ſeemed to be moſt oppoſite and ſtiffenecked: So we may much more and vpon ſtronger grounds of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon argue for our blind ſuperſtitious Countri-men, that they are not a reprobate people, whom God hath caſt away, and giuen ouer to deſperate blindneſſe and obſtinacy, neuer to be conuerted; becauſe not onely we our ſelues being many haue by Gods grace extended plentifully vnto vs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the word, and doe beleeue in Chriſt, and profeſſe true Chriſtianity; but alſo many noble worthies haue ſprung vp and flouriſhed in the Church of God, and ſhined as lights through this Kingdome, and the whole Chriſtian world, who being borne in our barren ſoyle, and in their child-bood muzled vp in ſuperſtition, ſo ſoone as God brought them to the light of the Goſpell in the vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the nurſeries of learning and true religion, they became famous and renowned profeſſors of diuinity, and moſt ſtout and ſtrong maintainers of the truth againſt Papiſts, and all other Heretiques. I cannot paſſe by in ſilence, but for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample will name and mention with honour and reuerence, that mirrour of learning and religion Doctor <hi>Whitakers</hi> our ſometimes worthy profeſſor in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> whoſe name is ſtill dreadfull to our aduerſaries, and his writings of greateſt eſteeme euen in forraigne Countries at this day, and his memorie euer bleſſed: Yea wee find by daily experience, that in thoſe pariſhes and places of our nature Country, which haue heretofore beene moſt grieuouſly ouer-runne with ignorance and ſuperſtition, while they wanted the meanes of knowledge the miniſtery of the word, and where the word at the firſt preaching thereof hath beene ſtrongly oppoſed; now by meanes of a conſtant miniſterie, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull preaching continued among them, the people doe become generally ſo zealous for the truth, ſo feruent in their zeale, ſo forward in their profeſſion, ſo ſtrict in their liues, &amp; in the worſhip of God, ſo oppoſit to all ſhadows of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, that ſome thinke they haue more need of the bridle
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:192164:10"/>then elſe ſpurre; like the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the wilderneſſe, who offered ſo frankly &amp; abundantly to the building of Gods ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, that there was found much more then enough for the ſeruice of the work, &amp; <hi>Moſes</hi> gaue commandment, and cauſed them by publike proclamation to be reſtrained from bringing any more, <hi>Exod.</hi> 36. I my ſelfe doe know, and can name for inſtance if neede require, diuers pariſhes which within my memorie, were deepely plunged in ſuperſtition, and euen drowned in ignorance, inſomuch that the name of a preacher was as much ſcorned of many, as the name of a babler, and of ſome as much hated as the name of an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique; but now of late yeares I haue ſeene with mine eyes ſuch a wonderfull alteration wrought by Gods grace and bleſing accompanying the labours of ſome holy and godly preachers ſent among them, that they are ready and willing to run many miles to heare ſermons, when they haue them not at home, and lay aſide all care of worldly profit, leauing their labour and worke on weeke dayes, to frequent pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like meetings for prophecy and expounding of Gods word, and hardly can a preacher trauell through their townes, and lodge there on any day in the week, but they will by impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie obteine a publicke ſermon from him, and in great troupes ſuddainly and vpon ſhort warning aſſembled, they will gladly and chearfully heare him with all reuerence and attention. And therefore as St. <hi>Paul</hi> from his owne example, &amp; the examples of a ſmall remnant of beleeuing <hi>Iewes,</hi> who by ſo many miracles &amp; much powerfull preaching of Chriſt himſelfe, and his extraordinarie Apoſtles and Prophets were called and drawne to beleue, did conclude that God had not reiected and caſt away the whole nation as reprobates paſt hope: So may we much more ſtrongly conclude, from the example of our ſelues who are many, and from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of thoſe worthy profeſſors and pillars of the Church, whom God hath raiſed vp out of our Country by ordinarie meanes, and moſt of all from the great multitudes of godly Chriſtians, who by hundreds and thouſands are daily called and turned by ordinarie preaching from the darkeneſſe of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:192164:10"/>ignorance, to the light of true knowledge, and from blind zeale and loue of poperie and ſuperſtition, to the feruent loue of the truth, and zealous profeſſion of the holy Goſpell of Chriſt: I ſay from theſe many examples, we may as vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtronger grounds of reaſon conclude, that God hath not caſt away our people, nor rejected our natiue Country, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſo many places keepes his word from them, as from a reprobate people neuer to be conuerted; but rather doth ſuffer them to liue ſo long in ignorance and miſerable blindneſſe, partly for a greater judgement on ouer-ruling Church-robbers, that he may bring on them and their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and families the blood of many ſoules, which periſh through their ſacrilege and couetouſneſſe: and partly to prouoke and ſtirre vp to pitty and charity, vs, whom he hath firſt conuerted, and to miniſter vnto vs matter of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity, and to giue vs occaſion to exerciſe that piety which we profeſſe, that our faith by liuely fruites of good workes, may be made to appeare more glorious to the eyes of the world, and may ſhine in the midſt of the Church, and among all the people of God.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, (Deare brethren and Country-men) for our full perſwaſion and ſteadfaſt aſſurance, that our natiue Country (notwithſtanding the ignorance and blindneſſe ouerſhado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing it, and the blind ſuperſtition poſſeſſing the people ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally in diuers parts thereof) is a place, which God hath choſen to put his name there, and our brethren the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof are a people choſen of God, and holy accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the election of grace; let vs call to remembrance and daily ſet before our eyes, what holy and excellent firſt fruites it hath brought forth vnto God, I meane holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and martyrs in the firſt times of the pure light of the Goſpell beginning to ſhine forth in this land. Among all godly martyrs wichin the dayes of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, were great builders of Gods Church by their ſound doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, painfull labours, and holy liues, and in the bloody reigne of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> ſealed the Goſpell with their blood, who more renowned in the hiſtorie of martyrs, then Mr.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:192164:11"/>
               <hi>Iohn Bradford</hi> a <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> man? whoſe godly writings and meditations able to make a ſtonie heart to bleede, remaine to the profit and comfort of Gods Church in all ſucceeding ages, whoſe conſtant profeſſion of the true faith vnto death, &amp; in the midſt of the fire was admired of his enemies, &amp; ſhall euer bee remembred while God hath an elect and faithfull people in this land, and whoſe memorie ſhall be bleſſed for euer. Among the godly, faithfull and learned men, whom this land brought forth in thoſe firſt times, and which ſhined forth as lights out of darkeneſſe, who after many cruell per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions and baniſhment which they endured for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, did ſuruiue her bloody reigne, and in the dayes of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of euer bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, flouriſhed in this Church, and were notable inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God in the reſtoring and eſtabliſhing of religion: who more admired for piety, prudence, learning and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then that moſt reuerend father in Gods Church, <hi>Edwin Sandes</hi> borne in <hi>Fournfells</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> who at the time of the deceaſe of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, being Doctor of diuinitie, and vice Chancellour of the vniuerſitie of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> did ſo wiſely and prudently behaue himſelfe in the midſt of thoſe troubles and that great confuſion, eſpecially in his publike ſermon which he was commanded by the Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland,</hi> to make againſt Queene <hi>Mary</hi> in that great aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where the Duke himſelfe with many nobles and men of warre were aſſembled to goe and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend her; that he gaue content to the Duke; and yet the Queene and her party could not from thence take any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage againſt him: who alſo after many troubles, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions and impriſonment, eſcaped with great difficultie, and fled beyond the ſeas, and from thence returning in the beginning of Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> reigne, after his learned diſputations againſt the Popiſh Biſhops, was in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that noble Queene and her wife counſell, eſteemed worthy of greateſt promotions in the Church, and was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred firſt to be Biſhop of <hi>Woreester,</hi> after Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and laſtly Arch-biſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> in all which ſeas he flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:192164:11"/>and was famous for his promoting of pietie, aduancing of learned preachers, and for publike workes of charitie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt for his erecting &amp; indowing of a free ſchoole at <hi>Hauxhead</hi> where he was borne, and where I one of the meaneſt of his kindred was in my youth trained vp in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; who alſo dying in a good old age, left behind him a no ble progenie and race of ſons, diuers of whom do vntill this day floriſh in wealth &amp; honor, and are famous for wiſdome, eloquence and experience in matters of religion and polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie obteined by their trauells in many forraigne Countries, and are men noted for other noble vertues in this ſtate and kingdome. The time would faile me, if I ſhould reckon vp by name all our Country-men famous in this kind, &amp; ſhould relate their worthy acts; as Mr. <hi>Alexander Nowell</hi> Doctor of diuinity and Deane of <hi>Paules,</hi> whoſe taſt of perſecution and baniſhment with other troubles and afflictions which he endured in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, wrought in him ſuch charity and compaſſion to the poore, that he became a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne as of piety towards God, ſo of pitty to the poore; and hauing ſpent his dayes and his wealth in continuall workes of charity, left alſo after him worthy monuments of his pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and charity, which remaine in <hi>Oxford</hi> and other places to the worlds end, for the benefit of young Schollers borne in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and for their education in learning and good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terature. I might alſo adde among all the reſt one of mine owne name and neare kinred, <hi>Iohn Walker</hi> Doctor of diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſometimes Arch-deacon and reſidenciary of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church in <hi>London,</hi> in whoſe breaſt godly zeale began to burne in his youth and tender yeares ſo feruently, that in the dayes of <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the eight when Popery began to decline, &amp; the way was but a preparing for reformation of religion, he together with the godly Arch-biſhop before named, out of their deteſtation and hatred which they bare to Popiſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Idolatry, did like <hi>Gideon</hi> ſecretly out, mangle and deface the Popiſh Images in the Church of <hi>Hauxhead,</hi> the place of their natiuity and mine; vpon ſuſpicion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was forced to flee out of his Country, and was ſecretly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:192164:12"/>nouriſhed and brought vp in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where he became a man of note for his great learning, and after perſecution and baniſhment which he ſuffered in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time, he was aduanced in the happy dayes of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to the dignities fore named, of which how worthy he was may appeare by his diſputation with <hi>Campian</hi> the Popes Challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger yet extant in print, againſt whom he was by the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like authority of the ſtate choſen and appointed to diſpute among other choſe learned men of the Kingdome. Now theſe with many others moſt godly and zealous profeſſors &amp; holy martyrs, being the firſt fruites of our natiue Country of <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> which it brought forth, and offered vnto God in the firſt day ſpring of the reuiuing Goſpell, I ſee no cauſe why we may not conclude, and vpon this ground aſſure our ſelues, that our Country and the generall body or mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of our people are an holy lumpe or maſſe choſen of God, and holy according to the election of grace; and that in due time they ſhall be generally conuerted and actually called to the knowledge and profeſſion of the true faith: For thus the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth reaſon &amp; conclude concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Country-men the <hi>Iewes Rom.</hi> 11.16. That <hi>if the firſt firſt fruites be holy, the lumpe alſo muſt be holy.</hi> Wherefore let no vaine ſcruples, no vncharitable doubtings, no euill ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes diſturbe vs in this good worke of piety and charity, nor withdraw our hearts, nor cauſe vs to withdraw our hands from a liberall contribution, which is ſo neceſſary and commodious for the aduancement of religion in the place of our natiuity, and which hath ſo much hope of gaining many ſoules of our brethren to God. Although I haue no warrant in Gods word to perſwade you with Popiſh motiues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> merit, that by cheerfull performance of this pious worke, you ſhall merit great rewards and bleſſings at Gods handes; no not if you ſhould ſell all that you haue, and beſtow on works of this nature; (becauſe all that we haue is Gods he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt it vs, and if we giue all to him we giue him but his owne; neither can we by all we haue be profitable to God, for he needs nothing of ours, our well doing is ako<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:192164:12"/>for our owne good and the good of our brethren, and ſerues to glorifie Gods grace in vs, not to adde any glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to him in himſelfe, and to magnifie his name and his goodneſſe before men, not to make him any better in his owne nature or perſon:) yet thus much I aſſure you, that if out of loue to godlineſſe, and out of humble obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Gods majeſtie, and true charity to the ſoules of his people, all proceeding from a liuely faith in Chriſt, you be ſtirred vp to ſhew your ſelues cheerefull, forward and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull in this pious and charitable worke, according to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility which God hath giuen to euery one of you; this your well-doing ſhall vndoubtedly receiue from God great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe of reward of his free grace and bounty, and for the merit of Chriſt; and the mere good workes that you do of this kind, the more euidence and teſtimony you ſhall haue of true faith and of the ſpirit of God dwelling in you, and making you one body with Chriſt, and partakers of his merits; which euidence ſhall not onely confirme you againſt all temptations, and comfort you in all afflictions, and make your proſperity ſweet vnto your ſoules in this life: but alſo ſhall ſtand vp in judgement for you, and proue you true members of Chriſt, that in him and for his merits ſake you may receiue the eternall kingdome and inheritance prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all the elect and faithfull before the foundation of the world. Now my deare brethren and beloued Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as I in this hope haue many yeares ſtudied and deſired to ſet this good worke on foote for the good of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and the ſaluation of my brethren, and as I haue ſpent both my labour and ſome money, and much precious time within the ſpace of theſe two yeares laſt paſt in attempting and beginning this worke, about the gathering of your names ſeuerally and particularly, and ſolliciting ſome of you, among whom I haue found diuers very forward, free and bountifull farre beyond expectation, and as I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy euen to the vtmoſt of my ability to goe before you by my example in this contribution: So I beſeech you that for the ſame hopes ſake, you will be ready to joyne with me
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:192164:13"/>and others who haue begun well, and that you will goe on with vs, and accompanie vs to the perfecting of this worthy worke. And for a concluſion of this exhortation, I humbly beſeech the Lord to enlarge your hearts according to the meanes and abilitie which hee hath giuen you, that you may extend the bowells of compaſſion to your brethren who ſit in miſerable darkneſſe and in the ſhadow of death, that they being called to the fellowſhippe of the ſame grace with vs, we may all glorifie Gods name before men in this life, and bee glorified of him with endleſſe glory in the life to come, and may all reigne with Chriſt our head the King of glory for euer world without end: To whom and to the word of whoſe grace I commend you all now and euer. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate Country-man, fellow-ſeruant in Chriſtianity, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all Chriſtian loue, GEORGE WALKER Paſtor of St. <hi>Iohn E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nangeliſts</hi> in <hi>Watling-ſtreete</hi> in LONDON.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:192164:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
